Guide to the Eva March Tappan Papers, 1881-1925
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Eva March Tappan Papers
1881-1925
Tappan, Eva March, 1854-1930
0.4 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Material relating to Tappan's work as a children's book author. Also includes some of her artwork, items relating to her time at Vassar College, and other biographical material.
Biographical Note
Eva March Tappan, the only child of a Baptist minister and a former school teacher, was born in Blackstone, MA. She was graduated in 1875 from Vassar, where she began to develop an interest in writing. After graduation she turned to teaching, going to Wheaton Seminary. Later she was able to begin graduate studies in English at the University of Pennsylvania, where she earned a Ph.D. in 1896. In the same year she published her first children’s book, Charles Lamb, the Man and the Author. The next year she took a position as head of the English department at English High School in Worcester, MA. By 1904 Miss Tappan had published nine more books, among them In the Days of Alfred the Great and Old Ballads in Prose, giving her sufficient income to retire from teaching. Her books, many of which were textbooks, were mostly devoted to history, biography, the retelling of folk tales, and literary classics such as The Chaucer Story Book. Eva March Tappan also translated many foreign folk tales, and her work placed her in the forefront of the trend toward historical and folk stories for children. Until her death Tappan lived quietly in Worcester, attending meetings of the local Vassar Club and the Boston Authors’ Club, but devoting most of her energy to the careful and thorough research which distinguishes her work.
Scope and Content Note
Manuscripts of Tappan's stories and histories written for children, 1881-1897 and undated; reminiscences from the 50th reunion of her Vassar class, 1925; her drawings, watercolors, and photographs; catalog from Worcester, Mass., English High School where she taught, 1898; a letter of recommendation for Tappan; her "Christmas Book," 1909-1918; and other miscellaneous items.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Organizations:
Vassar College. Class of 1875; Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae; English High School (Worcester, Mass.)
Subjects:
Children's literature--Women authors; Women authors, American; Women teachers
Document Types:
Paintings; Drawings (visual works); Photographs
VCL Categories
Children and Children's Literature; Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, April 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Sylvia (Sands) Paxton, VC 1962, and Bates College.
Container List
- Biographical information — address book (Folder 1.1)
- Biographical information — catalogue for Worcester English High School, 1898-1899 (Folder 1.1)
- Biographical information — letter of recommendation concerning E.M.T. (Folder 1.1)
- Biographical information — "Christmas Book,", 1909-1918 (Folder 1.1)
- Biographical information — Diaries, (3 items) (Folder 2.7)
- Manuscript — "The History That the Children Wrote", (TSs, 151p) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — "What We Know about Alfred the Great,", (TSs, 55p) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — Children's stories with no titles, (TS) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — "A Winter Sunday by the Sea,", 13 Feb 1881; (AMS, 21p) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — "A Summer Around the Bay of Fundy,", 30 Dec 1886; (AMS, 80p) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — "What Was the Secret of Jesus' Power?", 1897?; (TSS, 15p) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — Speech with handwritten note, (TS) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — One sheet of music of a hymn with words probably written by E.M.T. (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — "Friends That I Have Seen,", 3 Feb. 1884; (TS, 17p) (Folder 1.4)
- Manuscript — "The Young Man Who Used His Brains,", n.d.; (TS, 7p; MS, 14p) (Folder 1.4)
- Publications (Folder 1.5)
- Vassariana — Includes reminiscences at time of 50th reunion, 7 May 1925 (Folder 2.6)
- Photographs, (10 items) (Folder 1.2)
- Drawings, (65 items) (Folder 1.3)
- Watercolor sketches, (2 items) (Folder 1.3)
- Miscellaneous (Folder 2.8)